We're getting everything.
ばっちり撮れてますよ
He might be one dashing man, but to think he has such bad habits…
水が滴る　いい男であるのに
そんな趣味が　あるとは…
Ozu is in the same year as I am.
小津と　わたしは　同学年である
Because he hates vegetables and only eats instant food, he has an exceeding ghastly face that looks like it came from the dark side of the moon.
野菜嫌いで
即席物ばかり食べているから
何だか　月の裏側から来たような　顔をしていて
はなはだ不気味だ
Now's our chance!
チャ～ンス
He picks on the weak and sucks up to the strong. He's lazy and a devil.
弱者にむち打ち　強者にへつらい
怠惰で　あまのじゃく
My soul would have surely stayed unblemished had I not met him.
もし彼と出会わなければ　きっと　わたしの魂は
もっと　清らかだったであろう
And how did you get the duplicate key?
なぜ　お前は　合鍵を持っているのだ？
わたしは　城ヶ崎さんにも　信頼を　おかれていますからね
I've earned Jougasaki-san's trust, you see.
You back-stabbing bastard.
極悪人め
Oh, if you move anything, make sure to put it back exactly where you found it, okay?
ああ　物を動かしたら
びっちり　元の場所に　戻してくださいね
He's one serious clean freak.
あの人　かなりの潔癖症らしいですよ
潔癖症？ええ
Clean freak?
Yeah. That's why his girlfriend is like that instead of flesh and blood.
だから　生身の人間じゃなく
ああいう人を　彼女にしちゃうんですね
どういうことだ？
What are you talking about?
Over here.
こっちですあなたのような
A boor such as yourself whose mind is filled with sex probably couldn't understand.
エロで頭がいっぱいの野人には　分からないでしょうが
It's a form of extremely sophisticated love.
非常に　高尚な愛の形です
T-That's…
こっ…　これは…
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a brand-spanking new freshman university student and before my eyes were held out innumerable circle fliers far surpassing my personal information intake.
当時　ピカピカの大学１回生であったわたしの目の前には
個人の情報量を　はるかに凌駕する
無数のサークルのチラシが　差し出され
In each and every one of them I could see a door to that rose-colored campus life.
そのどれもが
「ばら色のキャンパスライフ」への　扉のように見えた
And the one I chose was…
そして　わたしが選び取ったのは…
There I was sure to lay my future of pure, sparkling gold.
そこには確かに　光り輝く　純金製の未来があった
My new cinema paradise with raven-haired maidens dancing on the silver screen!
黒髪の乙女たちが　銀幕に舞う
恋のニューシネマ　パラダイス
I decided to join that day in order to make 100 friends,
「みんなで楽しく　映画　作ってるよ」という
甘い言葉に惑わされ
友達１００人　作るべく
led astray by the naive words of
"Let's have fun making movies together."
その日のうちに　入会を決めてしまった　わたしは
手の施しようのない　アホだった
I was truly an idiot beyond all redemption.
"Sincerity vs. Authority"
And the movie circle "Misogi" which I joined that day
そして　その日　入会した　映画サークル「ＭＩＳＯＧＩ」では
会長である城ヶ崎先輩の下に
いまいましい独裁体制が　敷かれていたのだ
was under authoritarian rule by the president, Jougasaki-senpai.
Take 12, ready… Action!
テイク１２よーい　スタート！
"Teacher and Student Go to War"
「いくぞ　マーズ！」
Let's do this Mars!
Come at me!
「来い！」
"Jougasaki"
"I"
Cut!
カット！
う～ん…いまいち決まらんなぁ
It's just not right yet…
すまん　休憩の後　もう１テイク　やらせてくれ
Sorry 'bout this! After the break, let me do another take.
はい
Right!
Shit… To hell with that.
くそ…　やってられっか
Pervert!
ん？キャー　変態！
Wait! I…
あっ…　あっ　待って！ああ　ちょっと
While I was annoyed with Jougasaki-senpai's meaningless productions,
意味不明な　城ヶ崎先輩の演出の下
いら立っていた　わたしの傍らに
it was then that an ominous man stood beside me with a face of ill portent.
ひどく縁起の悪そうな顔をした不気味な男が立っていた
Are you from the dark side of the moon? Or perhaps an E.T.?
こ…　これは　月の裏側の住人か？
はたまた　Ｅ．Ｔ．か？
You say some pretty mean things.
あなた　ひどいことおっしゃる
There's no need to worry, I am your compatriot!
ご安心ください僕は　あなたの同志ですよ
That was my first contact with Ozu, as well as worst contact.
これが　小津との　ファーストコンタクトであり
ワーストコンタクトでもあった
All he does is parrot what he's read in 'how-to-make-movies' books.
しょせん　やつは　映画のハウツー本の受け売りです
I'd say it's Godard and Truffaut and the like,
ゴダールだの　トリュフォーだの　言ってますが
but the all-time best is actually that Titanic guy.
ホントは　オールタイムベストが　『タイタニック』なやつです
It's dangerous to have a guy whose head is only filled with boobs run the movie circle!
頭の中に　乳しかない男が
サークルを仕切ってるのは　危険ですよ
Movies must definitely not be allowed to be poisoned by commercialism!
映画は　断じて　商業主義に　毒されては　ならない！
Show us a movie circle the way it should be, with your own two bare hands!
あなたの手で　映画サークルの　あるべき姿を見せるのです！
For the purpose of raising the beacon of mutiny against Jougasaki-senpai's fiction,
わたしは　城ヶ崎先輩たちに　反逆の　のろしを上げるべく
I started filming my own personal movies.
独自に　映画を　撮り始めることにした
"Approach"
My first work: after the war in the Pacific, two men continue a battle of historic pranks,
まず　１作目は
太平洋戦争から続く　由緒あるいたずら
合戦を　引き継いだ　２人の男が
exhausting the limits of intelligence and physical strength.
A movie of overflowing war and violence.
知力と体力の　限りを尽くして戦う
バイオレンスあふれる映画であったが
Of course it was ignored and the only person in the theater that laughed was Akashi-san.
当然のごとく無視され
上映会で笑ったのは　明石さんだけであった
My second work: a sentimental movie about a man wavering between three women,
２作目は　『リア王』を下敷きとして
３人の女性の間を揺れ動く　男の心情を描いた作品であったが
patterned after King Lear.
It received a storm of vilification from the women's camp.
女性陣からは　罵詈雑言の嵐に遭った
And my third work: a man trapped in a never-ending maze of 4.5 tatami rooms
そして　３作目は　四畳半が　どこまでも続く迷路に
閉じ込められた男が　そこから　脱出するという映画であったが
and his attempts to escape from it.
「どこかで見た設定だ」と言われ　終わった
It was a DOA after people said "I've seen this premise before somewhere…"
Akahashi-san was the only one who gave me useful criticism.
ましなコメントをくれたのは　明石さんだけであった
Youjo-han
"The - End"
What was odd was that I couldn't help but think that the more effort I put in,
奇怪なのは　われわれが　努力すれば　するほど
the more Jougasaki-senpai's charisma seemed to rise.
城ヶ崎先輩のカリスマぶりが上がっていくように
思われて　ならないことであった
Our next work shall be Alexander the Great!
次の作品は
ずばり　「アレキサンダー大王」！
It will surely be a super grade-A piece of entertainment, the culmination of our work!
わたしの集大成と言うべき
超一級のエンターテインメントとなるだろう
So, everyone… Will you follow me?
みんな　ついてきてくれるな？
Yes!
はい！アブリューション！
Ablution!
When I think back on it now, I was used as leverage to increase his charismatic appeal.
今にして思えば
われわれは　先輩のカリスマぶりを持ち上げる
てこの支点として　利用されていたのである
Undaunted by Jougasaki-senpai, we attempted to announce a new romance film we were shooting,
城ヶ崎先輩に負けじと　われわれも
撮影中の　新作恋愛映画を　発表しようとしたが
but his faction was unanimously against it.
先輩連中は　こぞって反対
The enemy's first line of attack was Aijima-senpai,
敵の先方　相島先輩は　城ヶ崎先輩の右腕であり
Jougasaki-senpai's right-hand man,
who picked on us annoyingly.
しつこく　われわれを　いじめた人物でもある
上映スケジュールをごまかすという　アクロバティックな手法で
われわれを会場から締め出し
Using acrobatic tricks of the filming schedule and petty things
like turning off the electricity, hiding the key etc… He shut us out from the studio.
電源を落とす　鍵を隠すなどのせこい手を使われ
編集機材を借りるのに
土下座に近い屈辱を　なめたこともある
In the end no one would deal with me, and I was shut out of the movie circle.
結局　わたしは　誰からも相手にされず
ついに上映会から　締め出しを食ってしまった
How can he be so celebrated while we have to resign ourselves to this?
なぜ　あれが　あれほど歓迎され
われわれは　かくのごとき状況に　甘んじなければならぬのだ！
Now, now… The public is finicky.
まあまあ　大衆は保守的なんです
しかし　真の映画ならば　いつか認められます
But they will always recognize a film that's true to itself.
And when will that be!
いつの話だ！？
I want my recognition now!
即時　承認を求める！
You're quite selfish, you know that?
あなた　わがままな人ですね
あれだけ　やりたい放題やっておいて
If you're really so motivated, why do you have such a down-in-the-dumps look on your face?
何で　そんな　不景気そうな顔なんですか？
Shut up!
うるさい！
お前のせいで　有意義な学生生活が台無しになってしまった！
Thanks to you I've wasted my perfectly lovely college life!
あらら　それは　お互いさまじゃありませんか
Oh? I think you're to blame for that.
どうせ　あなたは　どんな道を選んだって
After all, it doesn't matter which path you take, you'll keep ending up right where you are now.
今みたいな　ありさまに　なっちまうんだ
ん？
Have we had this conversation before?
俺たち　前にも　こんな言い合いしてなかったか？
Of course not. It's déjà vu, just déjà vu.
してるわけないでしょ
デジャビュですよ　デジャビュ
そうかいずれにしても
I see…
At any rate, once I met you I put all my efforts into making you no good.
僕は　あなたに出会って
全力で　あなたを駄目にします
Why do you haunt me so?
お前はなぜわたしに付きまとうのだ
It's the way I show my love! We're connected by the black thread of fate, after all.
僕なりの愛ですよ
われわれは　運命の黒い糸で
結ばれているというわけです
"The Japan Trench"
So, here. This is Jougasaki-senpai's transcript.
それから　これ
城ヶ崎先輩の成績表です
He's got a great face, but what's inside his head is a mess.
あの人　表の顔では　ああして強がってますけど
内情はもう　ひどいもんですよ
He's in his eighth year?
８回生なのか
And moreover, his grades are dangerously low!
それに　恐ろしいほどの低空飛行
Why do you have something like this?
なぜ　お前は　こんな物を持っているんだ？
Please don't underestimate my information-gathering network.
わたしの情報網を　見くびらないでください
And to escape from this sad reality,
しかも　そんな現実から逃れるために
his heart has been more and more captured by the boobs of his female circle members.
彼は　ますます　女子部員の乳に　心を奪われています
That's also the reason behind that last infamous swimsuit audition.
今回の　破廉恥水着オーディションもそのためですよ
He filmed them in swimsuits?
水着で撮るのか？
There was no exhibitionism in the actual film.
いいえ
本編では　露出なんかありません
And that's exactly what made it so infamous.
だからこそ　破廉恥　極まりないんです
As an aside, here are the marks from the audition.
ちなみに　これが　そのときの採点表
"Name"  "Shape"  "Size"  "Remarks"
It shows the breasts' shape, angel, size, and separation.
おっぱいの形　向き　サイズ　距離を表にしているんです
He's completely mixed up his private fetish with his public behavior.
まったく　とんだ　公私混同ですよ
Okay, next!
はい　次
フフフッ　はい　次
Okay, next!
So then he's just a boob dictator!
それでは　ただの　おっぱい独裁者ではないか！
That's right. In short, he's nothing but a boob junkie.
そうですよ
要するに　やつは　単なる　おっぱいジャンキー
He's a boob drunkard.
おっぱいドランカーなんですよ
小津！わたしに　１つの考えがある
Ozu! I have an idea. Will you help me?
協力してくれるか？
What are you going to do?
どうしたんです？
Well, I'm going to leave the circle anyway.
どうせ　わたしは　いずれ　サークルを去ることになる
ならば　どうしても　最後に　城ヶ崎に　天誅を下したい！
So I at least want to bring down heavenly judgment on Jougasaki-senpai before the end!
Well, well, that's not very calm of you.
あらら　穏やかじゃないですね～
Understood. I'll follow you wherever you go, Director.
分かりました
どこまでも　ついていきますよ　監督
それは　義憤に駆られた　やむに　やまれぬ行動であった
And thus I was driven to action by my righteous indignation.
Now is the time to throw cold water on the people.
冷や水を浴びせる人間が　今こそ　求められている
Or to put it simply, I decided to film an exposé documentary on Jougasaki-senpai.
ありていに言えば　わたしは城ヶ崎先輩の
告発ドキュメンタリーを　撮ることにした
In order to save the underclassmen charmed by Jougasaki-senpai's meager charisma,
わたしは　城ヶ崎先輩の　ちっちゃなカリスマぶりに魅了された
I decided to willingly take on this villainous role myself.
下級生たちを救済すべく　恐ろしく　損な役回りを
進んで　買って出ることにした
What do you think, Master?
どうですか？　師匠
Well now…
さて
Still soft-balling it, right?
まだ　手ぬるいんですね
The man that Ozu had brought in as an adviser
アドバイザーとして　小津が連れてきたのは
城ヶ崎先輩を　古くから知る人物のようで
seemed to have known Jougasaki-senpai for a long time,
小津が　策謀の限りを尽くして　城ヶ崎先輩を
中傷する画面を作り出せば　作り出すほど
and Ozu schemed to his fullest extent to shoot
yet more and more libelous scenes of his discordant private life.
面白がり
相当な　個人的　確執があると　見て取れた
Ozu was like a kid in a candy factory,
小津は　水を得た魚のごとく　生き生きし
continuously manipulating the film to deviate from reality,
改変され続けたフィルムは　事実をも　逸脱し
and the exposé film became nothing more than a personal attack film.
告発映画は　単なる　個人的　中傷映画となっていった
これは　どうです？
How about this?
I wonder.
どうだろう
Maybe we should try going this far?
これぐらい　やっても　いいんじゃないですか？
Documentaries are deliberate, after all.
ドキュメントも　しょせん　意図的なものですから
Master, let's keep going on this, yes!
師匠　ガンガンいきましょうね
Well, it's sure looking like this will be an epoch-making work, don't you think?
いや～　どうやら　これは　エポックな作品になりますね
ちなみに　これ　クレジットは　監督が　１人で　お願い…
Oh and by the way, please only credit yourself, Director.
監督？
Director?
As I left the editing room and walked aimlessly around Kiyamachi,
編集室を出て　木屋町辺りを　当てもなく　歩いていると
under the overhang of someone's house
民家の軒下から
怪しげな妖気を　垂れ流している老婆がわたしを捉えた
I was caught by an old woman who emitted a suspiciously ghoulish aura.
This unplaceable aura was persuasive, and thinking logically,
その　えたいの知れない妖気には説得力があり
there was no way that the fortunetelling
わたしは　論理的に考えた
of a creature who emits such an aura could be anything but spot on.
これだけの妖気を　無料で　垂れ流している人物の
占いが当たらないわけがないと
What do you want to know?
何を　お聞きになりたいんじゃ？
Your face is a face of extreme impatience… You are unsatisfied.
あなたの顔は　大変　もどかしいという顔
不満ですね
I feel that you are not in a situation that you believe suits you,
どうも　今の環境があなたに
ふさわしくないと　お感じのようです
and I can sense your fiercely earnest talent.
あなたは　大変　まじめで　才能も　おありのようじゃし
Quickly did I tip my hat to the old woman's keen insight.
老婆の慧眼に　わたしは　早くも脱帽した
Anyway, I sense there is an opportunity you can't let pass by.
とにかく　好機を逃さないことが　肝心じゃ
An opportunity?
好機？
As in an excellent chance.
好機というのは良い機会ということじゃ
Yes, I know what that means…
それは　分かってます
This opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes.
好機は　いつでも　あなたの　目の前に　ぶら下がってございます
You must grab this opportunity and act on it.
あなたは　その好機を捉えて　行動に出なくちゃいけません
う～ん　何か　それ　前にも聞いた気が…
I have a feeling I've heard this before…
And if you do not…
さもないと！
you will walk this life as now, ever unchanging.
あなたは　また　今と変わらぬ　人生を歩むことじゃろう
That'll be 2,000 yen.
はい　２，０００円
Did you raise your prices?
値上がりしてませんか？
What does the viewer think is best?
客を一番に考えてるのは　何だ？
Spreading around emotions that can move a large number of viewers is basic etiquette.
んっ？たくさんの　お客さんと
感動を分かち合うための　エチケット
Jougasaki?
城ヶ崎
The Hollywood system is the best in the end.
結局　ハリウッドシステムが　一番いいということだ
んっ？　おう！
Hey there!
どうも
Hi.
How're you doing?
どうした？
ぼちぼちです
So-so.
It's too bad your proposal wasn't accepted.
企画が通らなかったのは　しょうがないと思うぜ
But movies are things everyone should see.
映画は　みんなが見るものだ
好きで　訳の分からないものを　作るのは　構わんが
I don't care if you make things you like that make no sense,
but if you want to show them to the other people, at least keep a minimum of etiquette.
観客に見せたいのなら
最低のエチケットは　守れ
Not only are you wasting the viewer's precious time,
観客の大事な時間を奪った上に
マスターベーションまで見せられるのは
it's basically like showing you masturbating to the other people! I couldn't stand that.
かなわんからな
Well, good luck, my brother!
まっ　頑張れ　兄弟
I don't think he gets it.
分かってないみたい
Ooh, he's scary…
やだ　怖い
There you are.
んっ　あっ　いた
Director! I've been searching for you.
監督　捜しましたよ
And so my determination to push forward
そうして　わたしは　城ヶ崎先輩の中傷映画
作りにまい進する決意をした
and create and libelous film against Jougasaki-senpai was renewed.
Below my feet ran the Takase River,
足元には　かつて
城ヶ崎先輩が　量産した自主製作映画と
同じぐらい　底の浅い高瀬川が流れていた
just as shallow as all the mass-produced independent films Jougasaki-senpai ever made.
Afterwards I returned to the editing room,
その後　わたしは編集室に戻り
３日間　寝ずに編集作業をした後
and on the morning of the fourth day,
after three days of editing without sleep,
４日目の朝　ついに　わたしの　２年間の集大成
とも言うべき…不毛なドキュメンタリーが
I finally completed the worthless documentary which one could say
was the culmination of my two prior years.
Finished
完成した
We're doing a screening. Please come.
上映会やりますんで　よろしく　お願いします
Your chance is during the staff introductions before they show the film.
上映前のスタッフ紹介の時間が　チャンスです
Head to the projector room then.
そのすきに　映写機へ
任せとけ！
Leave it to me!
This movie was created by the hard work of everyone in Misogi.
えー　この映画はわれわれ
ＭＩＳＯＧＩが　総力を結集して作ったもので
We really put our all into this.
ここには　われわれの全てが　詰まっている
これから　皆さんに　それを　ご覧いただこうと思います
I hope that you all will enjoy it!
Before we start, let me introduce the staff.
その前に　わが　スタッフを紹介します
This is Ozu-kun, who helped with the sound recording.
今回　録音で協力してくれた　小津君です
チッ　あの　八方美人めが
Playing both sides are we?
And next we have Akashi-san, who was in charge of the 3D and visual effects.
えー　続きまして　３Ｄや　ビジュアルエフェクト担当の明石さん
Akashi-san?
明石さん？
明石さん！？
I met Akashi-san during Jougasaki-senpai's shoot at Mt. Yoshida the previous year.
明石さんと　出会ったのは去年の夏
吉田山での　城ヶ崎先輩のロケであった
She was one year younger than me and in the engineering department,
彼女は　１つ下の学年で　工学部に属しており
and she was hired on staff for her technical skills.
その技術力を買われ　スタッフとして雇われていた
Always meticulous, with never an equipment mishap,
万事　手回しが良く　機材の扱いもそつない彼女は
she gained the trust of the other staff, but as she was not one to mince words,
スタッフの信頼を集めていたが
歯に衣着せぬ　物言いで
同回生からは　敬遠されていたようである
it seemed there was a distance between her and the people in her class.
With her sharp tongue, she held her own against Jougasaki-senpai,
舌鋒の鋭さにかけては　城ヶ崎先輩に　引けを取らず
先輩は　そのカリスマぶりに　傷が　付くのを恐れて
and although he took an interest in her chilly, intelligent demeanor (and her boobs),
彼女の冷ややかで　理知的な顔と　乳には　興味はあるものの
おいそれと　言葉を掛けられないでいた
he never spoke with her, fearful his charismatic flair would be damaged.
Akashi-san, you sure are fair skinned.
明石さんって　色　白いんだね
Me, fair-skinned?
わたしの肌の　どこが　白いんですか？
There are plenty of people with fairer skin than me, so on what basis do you say that?
肌の白い方は　ほかにも　いっぱい　いますし
何を基準に言ってるんですか？
With such a resolute denial and then cross-examination,
きっぱりとした否定と詰問に
それ以降　彼女に話し掛ける男はいなくなった
no man ever dared speak with her after that.
わたしは「明石さん　そのまま　君の道を
I sent off a fiery cheer of "Akashi-san, you just keep doing things your own way!" in my heart.
ひた走れ！」と　心の中で　熱いエールを送った
You created another idiotic movie…
また　アホなもの作りましたね
I'm sorry for making you watch such a worthless film.
ろくでもない映画を　見てもらって　すまんね
It was definitely worthless but I didn't hate it.
確かに　ろくでもなかったですけど
わたしは　嫌いじゃありませんでした
Now we will start the film!
えー　これより　上映を開始いたします
Please enjoy it to the end.
最後まで　ごゆっくり　楽しんでください
"Alexander"
Hey, maybe we should call it off…
おい　やっぱり　やめにしないか？
I can't bring myself to do it with Akashi-san here.
明石さんも　参加してたんじゃ　忍びない
What are you saying?
What happened to your pride as a filmmaker?
何を　言っているんです？
映画人としての誇りは　どうしました？
Speaking of which, you're on their crew!
というか　お前も
向こうのクルーじゃないか！
シッ！そろそろですよ
It's almost time.
Are you having fun, Alexander?
楽しんでるか？アレキサンダー
「酒では　晴れんよ　プトレマイオス」
Drinking will not clear my mind, Ptolemaeus.
「はい　ＯＫ！」
Ok, cut!
Nice work everyone!
「お疲れさまでした！」
「いやー　俺って　やっぱ　天才だわ！」
Oh, I'm definitely a genius.
Shut off the mic.
「マイク　オフって」
Wait, didn't he realize this was recording?
あれ？　これ　オンなの　気が付いてないの？
He's got a camera on him.
カメラ　ついてるぜ　キャーッ！！
I-I'm fine…
「だ…　大丈夫？」
Please take this!
「これ　もらってください！」
Thank you…
「あ…　どうも」
What's this
何これ？
Are those his?
先輩の？
What am I going to do?
I barely have enough money to eat, Mommy!
「どうすんだよ
米を買う　お金も　無いんだよ　ママ～」
T-This is…
こっ…　これは？
ゲッ…　嘘～っ！
No way!
What in the world?
何これ？
なななな…　城ヶ崎じゃねえのか？
You're kidding me… A wall of boobs?
まさか　壁に　おっぱい？
Is this non-fiction?
これって　ノンフィクション？
If so then… wow…
…にしたら　すごいよ
It's a lie, this is all a lie!
嘘よ　嘘よ　こんなの！
Impossible!
どーってことないわよ！
Hey, stop the film!
おい！　上映をやめろ！
Don't stop it!
やめるな！
I said stop it, stop it!
止めろってば　止めろ！
I'm home, Kaori.
「ただいま　香織」
Stop that! Not that!
やめろ！
そこは　やめろ
No!
やめてー！
Kaori-san, you're very pretty again today.
「香織さん　今日も　奇麗だよ」
Shall we go to sleep?
「そろそろ寝る？
Let's change your clothes…
着替えようか？」
Where is he? We'll smoke him out!
どこだあー！
いぶしだせ！
Yes!
はい！
You're really fast at running away.
あっ！　お前　逃げ足　速いなあ
だって　面倒くさいの嫌ですもん
Well, I don't like it when things get complicated.
There's no need to stop hanging out with me.
俺に　付き合って　辞める必要はないぞ
After forcing me to do all that, that's quite a thing for you to say.
あんなことさせといて　よく　そんなことが言えますねぇ
Ah, someone is coming.
あっ　誰か来た！
W-W-Wait!
まっ…　待って！　あっ
あぁっ！　あっ　明石さん…
Akashi-san.
You created yet another idiotic movie…
また　アホなものを　作りましたね
They didn't stop the screening?
上映…　止められてなかった？
The viewers found it interesting, after all.
観客が　面白がってますから
But Jougasaki-san's faction is looking for you.
けど　城ヶ崎さんたちは　先輩を　捜しています
もうすぐ　ここへ来るでしょう
He'll probably be here soon.
Right, understood.
うん…　分かった
Well, I'm glad the people watching had a laugh.
観客が　笑ってるなら　まあ　よかろう
それが　あいつの言う　エンターテインメントだ
That's what he'd call entertainment.
I preferred your earlier films.
わたしは　これまでの方が好きでした
今度のは　品性を疑います
This one was of questionable character.
いいんだ　今回は　作り逃げだ
Whatever… It was a hit-and-run.
先輩は　アホです
You are an idiot.
そのとおりだ
You got that right.
And you haven't kept your promise yet.
まだ　先輩は　約束も果たしていません
約束？
Promise?
Whatever, hurry up and escape.
うっ！　いいです
ほら　早く逃げてください
Indeed, now, Akashi-san, fare thee well!
うむ　それでは　明石さんよ　さらばじゃ！
Do not be fooled by Jougasaki's magic!
城ヶ崎マジックに　だまされちゃいかんぞー
Do I seriously look like a fool to you?
そんな　ボケナスに見えますか？　わたしが
And so I left behind the site of my unproductive, agonizing struggle over the past two years.
こうして　わたしは　２年間　不毛な苦闘に
挑んでいた空間を　後にした
これは？
What's this?
When I returned to the boarding house,
下宿に戻ると
先日　小津にもらったカステラが
何者かによって　食い散らかされていた
someone had sloppily eaten the Castella that Ozu had brought me the other day.
For some reason I was tired.
何だか　疲れた
I felt like my reason had crumbled to pieces like that Castella.
理性がまるでこのカステラのように
ボロボロ　崩れていくかに思えた
I was thinking that my next film would be about true love.
次の映画は思い切って　純愛映画をやろうと思う
A true love film?
純愛映画…
A love romance where two people tied by fate
運命に結ばれた２人が
立場　年齢　性別を超えて　結ばれる　ラブロマンスだ
would overcome their positions, ages, and even sexes.
It sounds like it's going to turn into something weird again.
それはまた　変なものに　なりそうですね
Let go! Let go, Akashi-san!
放せ！
放すんだ　明石さん
I squished it… I s-squished it…
むにゅっとしてました　むにゅっと
Now, now, calm down.
まま　落ち着きたまえ
すみません
I apologize. I am not fond of moths.
ガは　苦手なんです
These are called Mochiguman, and they come in sets of five, but I have lost one.
これは　モチグマンといって
５匹で　一揃いなのですが
１匹　なくしてしまって
Worry not! As this Earth is round, you are sure to meet once again.
心配するな
どうせ　地球は丸いのだ
いつかまた会える
Or if you'd like, I'll help search for it.
何なら　わたしが　捜してあげてもいい
I'd rather you make that movie a reality.
それより　さっきの映画を　実現させてください
Then it's a promise.
約束ですよ
Promise? So that's it…
約束って　そうか…
This opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes.
好機は　いつでも　あなたの目の前にぶら下がってございます
…but I didn't hate it.
わたしは　嫌いじゃなかったですけど
Don't get carried away with your dreams. That's what I kept telling myself.
「夢を見るのも　たいがいにしろ」そう
わたしは自分に言い聞かせた
I had no confidence in that I could comprehend a woman who could understand my selfish movies.
あんな　身勝手な映画を理解してくれる女性を
わたしは　理解する自信がない
And so I tried watching my latest, unfinished film.
わたしは　完成しなかった最新のフィルムを見てみることにした
I can't shake off the feeling of regret
あの運命の時計台で　映画サークル
「ＭＩＳＯＧＩ」を選んだことへの
for choosing the movie circle "Misogi" in front of that fateful clock tower.
後悔の念は　振り払えない
If I had joined some other circle, like for instance the human flight circle "Birdman",
もし　あのとき　例えば鳥人サークル
「バードマン」に入っていたら
I would have surely spent quite a different two years.
わたしは　もっと別の　２年間を送っていたであろう
「お前は　いつも　わたしに　付きまとってくれるね」
You will always haunt me so, won't you?
「これが　わたしなりの愛ですわ」
That's the way I show my love.
Keep it to yourself!
そんなもん　いらんわい！
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!